Guide to the William Louis Calver Papers 1894-1940 (Bulk 1900-1940) MS 96
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
William Louis Calver Papers
1894-1940 (Bulk 1900-1940)
MS 96
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.5 Linear feet (6 boxes)
Correspondence and papers, 1894-1940, including material concerning the N-YHS Field Exploration Committee (formed in 1918) and correspondence with eminent American, English, and French military experts, antiquarians, and military artists.
Provenance
Donation of William L. Calver, 1940.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Biographical Note
William Louis Calver (1859-1940) was a military antiquarian and chairman of the New-York Historical Society's former Field Exploration Committee from the time of its formation in 1918 to the time of his death. His research and archaeological investigations on Revolutionary War campsites and forts and War of 1812 military sites along the Canadian frontier formed the background of articles published in the NYHS Quarterly Bulletin and subsequently republished in History Written with Pick and Shovel.
Scope and Content Note
Interspersed among the papers of William Louis Calver are photostat copies of published material and other relevant material. Though the work of the Field Exploration Committee did not begin until its formation in 1918 and continued to the time of Calver's death, the collection of Calver papers actually antedate the committee's functions and include Calver's correspondence with other eminent American, English, and French military experts, antiquarians, and military artists, and form the basis for his expert writings on uniforms of the American, British, and French armies. An account of the work of William Louis Calver and his associates and of the Society's Field Exploration Committee is to be found in Richard J. Koke's introduction to History Written with Pick and Shovel.
Arrangement
The collection is roughly organized by type of material: papers relating to the NYHS Field Exploration Committee, data, reprints and drafts of articles, and letters.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
For related materials at the Society, see BV Calver and Calver's "Collection of old British Army buttons, badges, accoutrements and costumes."
New-York Historical Society. Field Exploration Committee; Archaeology; Buttons; Military uniforms; New York (N.Y.); United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; United States--History--War of 1812
- Container List
  - NYHS Field Exploration Committee: Papers re: the Committee (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NYHS Field Exploration Committee: Newspaper articles re: the work of the Committee (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Calver from Edwin A. Barber, Director, Pennsylvania Museum re: ceramics found in British camps, 1913-1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Data re: Oscar Theodore Barck, Sr., member of NYHS Field Exploration Committee (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters written by Reginald Pelham Bolton (1856-1942) and data relative to his writings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Data assembled by Reginald Pelham Bolton and Calver re: so-called "magazine" within Fort Washington, Fort Washington Avenue at 183rd Street, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Data re: to Inwood Hill Park on upper Manhattan Island (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Calver from A. M. Brooking, Director, The Hastings Museum, Hastings, Nebraska, 1925-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Calver from Howard Bullis, Brooklyn, NY re: archaeological discoveries on Long Island, NY, 1922-1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Data and letters of Calver re: research and his activities (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Calver to Oscar Theodore Barck, Sr. re: their activities and work of the NYHS Field Exploration Committee on various Revolutionary War and War of 1812 military sites; and letters written by Calver during his trip to Palestine to excavate Crusader castle of Montfort for The Metropolitan Museum of Art (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Calver to Reginald Pelham Bolton, Work of NYHS Field Exploration Committee at Fort Washington, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Reprint of article by Calver, "The British Army Button in the American Revolution," in NYHS Quarterly Bulletin, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Original drafts by Calver for article, "Two Additional Belt Plates and Another Cartridge-Box Badge of the British Army in the American Revolution," published in NYHS Quarterly Bulletin, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Original draft by Calver for article, "A Sword-Belt of the Revolution," published in Fort Ticonderoga Museum Bulletin, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript draft by W.L. Calver for article on sleeve links and civil dress buttons (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Original carbon of article by W.L. Calver, "Recollections of Northern Manhattan," written in March 1932, and published in NYHS Quarterly, January 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript draft by Calver, "Camp Robinson's Farm at Garrison, Putnam County, New York," in the Hudson Highlands, explored by the NYHS Field Exploration Committee (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Article by W.L. Calver for radio talk on archaeological work and activities of NYHS Field Exploration Committee (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Typescript of lecture by W.L. Calver at NYHS on Hudson Highlands, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Data on Major General John Small for article by Calver published in Fort Ticonderoga Museum Bulletin, [1936] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between Calver and Bottet and Lacault re: French 18th century uniforms, 1908-1916 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Data on Phoenix buttons and King Christiphe of Haiti, [1920-1930] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Data on buttons (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Canadian and War of 1812 material (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence of Calver with C. S. Campbell re: Niagara frontier forts, [1908-1930] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Calver with Walter S. Chattin re: button collection of Reginald L. Hart and American Buttonists Society, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Calver correspondence with W. G. Crozier, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Calver from Robert S. Duncan re: military data, 1928-1933 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters and data re: military matters from John War Dunsmore, artist and member of NYHS Field Exploration Committee (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters and data exchanged between Calver and Alexander R. Cattley, British Military expert and artist, re: uniform equipment, [1924-1939] (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters and data exchanged between Calver and Luis Fenollosa Emilio, button authority, re: buttons, 1903-1908 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Data on forts (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Calver from Dwight Franklin relative to uniforms, 1932-1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters and data, Harold B. Hayden re: Isle aux Noix on Canadian border, Richlieu River, Lake Champlain, [1924-1928] (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Calver from Charles Gaunt re: military equipment, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Calver from R.W. Geary relative to Niagara frontier and Lundy's Lane Historical Society, 1925-1933 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Calver from Colonel Charles Haggard, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Calver from Reginald W. Hart re: military equipment, 1902-1908 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Calver from Leslie G. Hilborn re: military equipment and buttons, [1927-1928] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Calver from Charles B. Hill-Tout re: Hill-Tout's collection of military relics, 1929-1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Calver from Alfred F. Hopkins, Museum Curator, Colonial National Monument, re: belt plate, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hudson Highland Revolutionary War buttons and relics, Payment to George B. Cusley and Sergeant Cephas Fleming, U.S. Army, for their collections, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Calver from William Kirby, Niagara-on-the-Lake, Canada, re: Niagara River forts and relics, 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Calver from Charles La Cault, French military artist, re: uniforms and military matters, 1909-1914 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Calver from B.E. Law, re: relics, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Calver from A.C. Lovett re: military data, 1913-1920 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Calver from A. MacWilliam re: buttons, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Calver and correspondence with Major Samuel Milne, antiquarian and author re: British regimental equipment in American Revolution [1894-1909], 1914 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Calver from Morristown National Historic Park re: Morristown and Revolutionary War buttons and relics, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Calver from J.B. Nightingale re: buttons and relics, 1922-1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Data on Calver's excavation of Crusader Castle of Montfort, Palestine for the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings and data relative to Palestine, collected by Calver in connection with his excavation of the Crusader Castle of Montfort (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Letters to Calver from H.G. Parkyn re: to British military relics, 1913-1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Data and correspondence re: 20th Regiment Foot and British military data, [1927-1933] (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Data collected by Calver and Reginald Pelham Bolton on Revolutionary War army huts (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Calver from Percival W. Reynolds, British military artist re: military dress and data, 1909-1931 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Calver from Edward H. Rogers re: relics, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Calver from Major J.H. MacKay Scobie, Curator, Scottish National Military and Naval Museum re: buttons and military subjects, 1930-1936 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Data and correspondence re: Scovill Manufacturing Company, Waterbury, Connecticut, re: buttons manufactured by the company, 1943-1945 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Calver from George O.W. Servis re: military collections and data, 1904-1938 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Calver from Starr S. Sherwood, 1922-1928 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Letters and data re: Revolutionary War fort sites on Staten Island, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Calver from Carlyle Smith re: firearms, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Calver from G.W. Snook re: military data, 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Calver from Colonel Daniel Stevens re: buttons, 1902-1904 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Assorted data of Dr. William S. Thomas, member of the NYHS Field Exploration Committee re: Revolutionary War military camps, 1922-1929 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Letters written by William L. Calver to Dr. William S. Thomas, 1917-1925 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Data on Fort Ticonderoga, collected by Calver in connection with his excavation of the Crusader Castle of Montfort (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Letters to Calver from Frederick P. Todd re: American military equipment, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Data on troops (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Data on 17th Regiment of Foot (British Army) (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Data on various subjects (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Calver and data from Dr. J.C. Webster, military antiquarian and author, re: buttons and military data, 1908-1918 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Data on Williamsburg, Virginia (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Data and article by Calver on Revolutionary War army huts (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Edgar N. Williams (Box 6, Folder 5)